<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A thanksgiving-sermon for the peace: preach'd at St Michael Crookedlane, December the 2d, 1697. By James Gardiner, M.A. rector of the said parish.</title>
            <author>Gardiner, James, 1637-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G228A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223633</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833922</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833922</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1830:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A thanksgiving-sermon for the peace: preach'd at St Michael Crookedlane, December the 2d, 1697. By James Gardiner, M.A. rector of the said parish.</title>
                  <author>Gardiner, James, 1637-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for B. Aylmer, at the Three Pigeons against the Royal Exchange in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVII. [1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Thankſgiving-Sermon FOR THE PEACE: PREACH'D AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Michael Crookedlane,</hi> DECEMBER the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JAMES GARDINER,</hi> M. A. Rector of the ſaid Pariſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:38400:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38400:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS XXIV. 2, 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>— Seeing that by Thee we enjoy great Quietneſs, and that very worthy deeds are done unto this Nation by thy Providence,</p>
                  <p>We accept it always, and in all places (moſt noble Felix) with all Thankfulneſs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot but with <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Adoro Scripturae plenitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. <hi>Tert, lib. cont. Hermog.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>adore</hi> the <hi>exquiſite</hi> and <hi>compleat Fulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> for <hi>this</hi> one thing amongſt many others, That let the <hi>Occaſion</hi> be what it will, of calling a Solemn Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, whether for <hi>Prayer</hi> or <hi>Praiſe,</hi> to receive <hi>Inſtructions, Directions,</hi> or <hi>Encouragement</hi> to any Duty, <hi>general</hi> or <hi>particular;</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Caſe be, you cannot dip into the <hi>Sacred</hi> Leaves, but you ſhall preſently meet with ſome Paſſage or other, that will be pertinent to the Buſineſs in hand.</p>
            <p>Such are <hi>theſe</hi> Words that I have pitch'd upon to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain you, as an <hi>Helper</hi> of your <hi>Joy</hi> upon <hi>this Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving;</hi> (for ſuch Feſtivals as <hi>theſe,</hi> come not within the Cenſure of our Nicer Spirits; thoſe who have quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel'd with the reſt, the Feſtivals of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and his <hi>Virgin Mother,</hi> do yet allow of <hi>Feriae repentinae, &amp; ex re natâ inſtitutae,</hi> as they pleaſe to phraſe it; ſuch as are inſtituted and ordain'd upon New Emergencies)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Taken by themſelves,</hi> they look as if they had been Penn'd for the very purpoſe, as if they had been <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd</hi> and fitted only to <hi>this</hi> Occaſion, exactly circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38400:3"/>and proportion'd to the Time. <hi>Seeing that by Thee we enjoy great Quietneſs, and that very worthy deeds are done unto this Nation by thy Providence; We accept it always, and in all places</hi> (moſt Dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign) <hi>with all Thankfulneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's worth obſerving, That we are ſometimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>honour</hi> Bad Princes, but never to <hi>rejoice</hi> in them, as we ought to do in Good. Then, <hi>Sing, O heavens,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.7, 13.</note> and be joyful, O earth; break forth into ſinging, O mountains.</hi> Few Virtuous Men, but fewer Virtuous Princes; many a righteous man in <hi>Sheep skins</hi> and <hi>Goat-skins,</hi> but few in <hi>Ermins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if ever Subjects had Cauſe to glory in a Prince, <hi>We</hi> are the Men. The Peoples Argument to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion was but a <hi>petty</hi> Topick to <hi>this;</hi> they tell him that <hi>He was worthy for whom he ſhould do this;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 7.5.</note> 
               <hi>for he loved their nation, and built them a ſynagogue:</hi> Whereas <hi>our</hi> Sovereign not only <hi>loved,</hi> but <hi>ſaved our</hi> Nation; and not only <hi>ſaved</hi> our Nation, but <hi>crowned</hi> it at once; (We have Him in the Throne <hi>before our Hopes,</hi> though <hi>later than our Wiſhes:</hi>) Nay, ſaved and crowned <hi>Three</hi> Nations at <hi>once,</hi> and bleſt them with <hi>Peace;</hi> and merits to govern much larger Territories than he yet poſſeſſeth.</p>
            <p>We have a Sovereign that is a Sovereign indeed, in the ſenſe of <hi>Medicine</hi> as well as <hi>Majeſty;</hi> of an <hi>healing</hi> Virtue; <hi>Majeſtas &amp; Amor;</hi> Majeſty and Mercy lodg'd in his Royal Breaſt; a Sovereign like our <hi>Saviour,</hi> that can be <hi>touch'd with the feeling of our Infirmities:</hi> A Prince that takes <hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure</hi> in all <hi>Generous</hi> Actions; whom <hi>Foreign</hi> Crown'd Heads admire for his <hi>Wiſdom, Cloſeneſs, Proweſs,</hi> and <hi>Activity,</hi> and court for his <hi>Friendſhip;</hi> and yet is endued with that <hi>Steddineſs</hi> of Mind, that doth not grow <hi>giddy</hi> with its <hi>own</hi> Height. A Prince, whoſe Auguſt Majeſty hath
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38400:3"/>not only Enobled the Nation, and recover'd its loſt Reputation; but who Stands the <hi>World's Triumphant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpire,</hi> maintains the <hi>Balance,</hi> and has <hi>Even Now</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Check (as a Noble <hi>Anceſtor</hi> of <hi>his</hi> from whom <hi>he</hi> is deſcended <hi>did</hi> before to the <hi>Swelling</hi> Monarchy of <hi>Spain,</hi> when ſhe thought to have graſp'd all the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Europe;</hi>) to <hi>One</hi> whoſe <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Acquists</hi> grew too big for the common Safety of our Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nations, and obliged him <hi>to come bending unto Him;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 60.14. Luk. 14.32.</note> to ſend an Ambaſſage, and deſire conditions of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>which</hi> Things, amongſt the reſt, I queſtion not in the leaſt but the <hi>very</hi> Hearts of his <hi>Enemies</hi> admire him in <hi>Secret;</hi> and that the <hi>very diſaffected</hi> Party of the Nation themſelves, if they look round about, could not name any One King now reigning in <hi>Christendom</hi> whom they would have to rule over them than <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> under whoſe Government at preſent they are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy. Whoſe <hi>Virtues</hi> ſhall <hi>out-live</hi> himſelf, and <hi>many</hi> Generations ſhall fare the better for <hi>him.</hi> Thus <hi>Solomon</hi> the Father, and <hi>Rehoboam</hi> the Son, and many more were preſerved from Ruin for <hi>David</hi>'s ſake; and in the days of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (above 300 Years after) <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> her ſelf, in great diſtreſs, was defended by GOD for his <hi>own</hi> ſake, and for his Servant <hi>David</hi>'s ſake. Religious Princes and Potentates are an <hi>Extraordinary</hi> Bleſſing. Iſa. 1.26 <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges, as at the firſt,</hi> &amp;c. a Mercy repreſentative of <hi>all</hi> the good GOD has in his Thoughts to beſtow upon <hi>Judah.</hi> He makes choice of <hi>this</hi> as the fitteſt Interpreter of his large Heart, as <hi>that</hi> which might beſt aſſure them of his Love. The Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> without a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> was able to ſee happy days coming upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> from the <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom</hi> She obſerved in their Prince. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.8. <hi>Becauſe thy GOD loved Iſrael to eſtabliſh them for ever, therefore made he</hi> Thee <hi>King over them to do Judgment, and Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:38400:4"/>
            <p> I know (My Brethren) it's a <hi>Sin</hi> to flatter Kings; and let it be <hi>Treaſon</hi> if you will; but a <hi>good One ought daily to be praiſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ 72.15.</note> But leſt I ſhould be challenged for <hi>ſo bold</hi> an attempt as the giving any <hi>Character</hi> of His <hi>Moſt Sacred Majeſty,</hi> (for <hi>Every</hi> Pencil is not permitted to draw a <hi>King's</hi> Picture;) and believing that <hi>Great Things</hi> and <hi>Greater Perſons</hi> are not to be treated, or ſo much as treated of, but with the greateſt <hi>Deference, Caution,</hi> and with the moſt <hi>profound Submiſſions;</hi> inſtead of <hi>inditing</hi> ſo <hi>good</hi> a <hi>Matter,</hi> I ſhall at preſent only <hi>ſpeak of the Things</hi> that are fairly laid down in the Text, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The very worthy deeds done unto <hi>this</hi> Nation by his Providence, or <hi>Prudence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The great Quietneſs, or <hi>Peace,</hi> which, by his Conduct, and Management, we <hi>now</hi> enjoy. The <hi>Firſt</hi> of which came to paſs when he was our glorious <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer;</hi> the Second now He is Our <hi>Lawful</hi> and <hi>Rightful</hi> King. And then</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) I ſhall wind up the Diſcourſe with ſome <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical</hi> Deductions. And</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The very worthy Deeds done unto <hi>this</hi> Nation by his Providence. Such, which our <hi>Childrens Children</hi> ſhall Sing the Story of, whilſt their <hi>pleaſed</hi> Parents <hi>ſmile</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into <hi>Tears</hi> of <hi>Joy</hi> that they liv'd to ſee the truth of the <hi>Strange Revolution;</hi> which to After ages may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly wear the <hi>Face</hi> of a <hi>Romance,</hi> and either the <hi>Thing</hi> it ſelf concluded to be only the extravagant <hi>Sallies</hi> of ſome <hi>Hiſtorians;</hi> or elſe the <hi>Perſon,</hi> whom Providence has Selected out of the Maſs of Mankind, to be an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> what Wonders the Almighty can do for <hi>thoſe</hi> he has a <hi>Strange</hi> Kindneſs for.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you in what a dreadful Poſture our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs both <hi>Civil,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtic,</hi> ſtood at <hi>that</hi> Juncture when our <hi>almoſt unpreſidented</hi> Deliverance was wrought for us. They were (as One ſpeaks of the State of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38400:4"/>Empire in his Time) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, upon the Edge of the Razor. The Nation, ſuch were its <hi>agonies</hi> and <hi>convulſions,</hi> ſeem'd like the Roll, Ezek. 2.10. <hi>written within and without, Lamentation and Weeping and Woe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Invaſions upon our Rights were we long and ſad Spectators of! The <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>England</hi> at that Time we might find in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.14. <hi>Judgment was turned backward, and Juſtice ſtood afar off; Truth was faln in the Streets, and Equity could not enter.</hi> Our Foundations were out of courſe, and, like the <hi>Earth,</hi> our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeemed to hang without any hold.</p>
            <p>Our Laws (the common Inheritance and Patrimony of every Free-born Subject, the Security of all that can be valuable in this World) <hi>profeſſedly</hi> run down; and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> and <hi>Trials</hi> were only become the <hi>Words</hi> of <hi>Form</hi> to be made uſe of for deſtroying us by <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Method;</hi> and were only the <hi>Solemnities.</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of our Ruin. No Man's Fence was Strong enough to reſiſt <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious</hi> Judges, and <hi>ſuborn'd</hi> Juries. Prerogative (which is only a Power to preſerve People on <hi>extraordinary</hi> Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions) was made the great Engine of their Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Men by Law <hi>unqualify'd</hi> for any Truſt, were thruſt into all Offices of Truſt; and thoſe who were Traitors in the Eye of the Law, had the chief Management of Affairs.</p>
            <p>The Nurſeries of the Clergy were aſſign'd over to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; and the Miniſters of Religion were enjoin'd, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Laws in force, to proclaim Liberty to their Pariſhioners to go to Maſs, or where they pleaſed; and threaten'd with a Severe Proſecution for their Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliance, which in part was Executed by impriſoning the <hi>Fathers</hi> of our Church.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:38400:5"/>
            <p> Publick <hi>Maſs</hi>-houſes, and <hi>Schools</hi> for the <hi>corrupting</hi> of <hi>Youth,</hi> were ſet up in ſeveral parts of the Kingdom. The Wolves, and <hi>profeſſed Adverſaries</hi> of <hi>our</hi> Church, were intruſted for the providing <hi>Pastors</hi> for it; the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and other Popiſh Prieſts, having the <hi>Choice</hi> of our Biſhops, and the diſpoſal of all ſuch Eccleſiaſtical Preferments as belonged to the Crown.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Standing</hi> Army was kept up in the Time of Peace, meerly to over awe the People, and deter them from aſſerting their Rights; to bring us into <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> that they ſhould all have a Right to every thing of ours, nor leave us any other way to help our ſelves, and eaſe our ſad Complaints, but our <hi>private Prayers,</hi> and our <hi>dry Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such as would not comply to promote their Popiſh Deſigns, were turn'd out of the <hi>Court, Corporations,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſions</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Lieutenancy:</hi> Not a Few debarr'd of their <hi>way of Livelihood;</hi> and a Reſolution taken to ſuffer none to exerciſe any <hi>ſuch Employment</hi> as required a <hi>Licenſe,</hi> unleſs they would make the <hi>like</hi> Engagement.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament,</hi> which ſhould Redreſs our Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, was no longer allowed the <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Voting;</hi> but the <hi>Lords,</hi> and <hi>all others</hi> who were likely to be <hi>Members,</hi> were <hi>Cloſetted;</hi> and all Arts uſed to induce them to betray their Liberties.</p>
            <p>The Nation no longer permitted the free Choice of their Repreſentatives; but <hi>Threatnings,</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces,</hi> and all Methods made uſe of to determine them to <hi>ſuch Tools</hi> as the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſhould think fit to <hi>Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> to them.</p>
            <p>And at laſt, (to omit other Publick Grievances, too tedious to enumerate on <hi>ſuch</hi> a Day as <hi>this,</hi> for their Name was <hi>Legion</hi>) a <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> was introduced into the World; the <hi>ill</hi> Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38400:5"/>of which Buſineſs the very Papiſts themſelves complain'd of.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Prince of</hi> Wales (<hi>ſaith One of them under the Mask of a Proteſtant, in a virulent Paper againſt his preſent Majeſty, Entituled</hi> England's Criſis, <hi>or</hi> The World well amended, <hi>printed in</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) <hi>I cannot but confeſs ſome people managed, as if they deſign'd either</hi> that we ſhould not believe at all, <hi>or</hi> if we did, <hi>our</hi> Belief <hi>ſhould be as</hi> implicit <hi>as to</hi> Succeſſions <hi>and</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances here, <hi>as that of the</hi> Romaniſt <hi>is in the</hi> Expectation <hi>of the</hi> Kingdom <hi>of</hi> Heaven.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, We were dealt withal as <hi>Thieves</hi> do by them they <hi>Rob;</hi> we were <hi>bound</hi> and <hi>gagg'd</hi> tha we might not ſtir to help <hi>our ſelves,</hi> nor cry out for the help of <hi>Others.</hi> We were <hi>preſt out of Meaſure, above Strength;</hi> inſomuch that our Heart <hi>dy'd</hi> within us, and we <hi>deſpair'd</hi> even of <hi>Life,</hi> and had the <hi>Sentence</hi> of <hi>Death in our ſelves.</hi> We were juſt Sinking <hi>under</hi> the Waves, <hi>upon</hi> which we had walked ſo long <hi>not without</hi> a <hi>Miracle;</hi> when lo! the <hi>Saviour</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> Stretched forth his Arm, and ſaved Us, and deliver'd us from <hi>ſo</hi> great a Death. He rais'd up a <hi>Man</hi> that <hi>ſcorned</hi> Eaſe and Pleaſure, and Dangers;
<note place="margin">Acts 16.11.</note> and <hi>inſpir'd</hi> his Royal Breaſt with a vigorous and an active Fire, <hi>to come over and help</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Innocence; which was no ſooner done, but in <hi>a Moment,</hi> in <hi>the twinkling of an Eye,</hi> this great <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> of dangers was broken, diſſipated, and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy'd; and we were <hi>Surpriz'd</hi> with <hi>Salvation. It ſhall come to paſs,</hi> ſaith <hi>Zachary, that at</hi> Even-time <hi>it ſhall be</hi> Light. When we were expecting nothing but <hi>darkneſs</hi> (for what is the <hi>Evening</hi> but a <hi>Sepulchre</hi> prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the <hi>Light?</hi>) behold <hi>then</hi> it was <hi>Light, perfect day.</hi> The Matter was brought about by <hi>His</hi> Conduct and Providence, without undergoing the Miſchiefs of having <hi>our Country</hi> made the <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>War:</hi> The <hi>Perſons</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> (what by <hi>guilty Fears,</hi> and <hi>Cowardiſe;</hi> what by a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Infatuation</hi> that ſeized them) <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Power and Might</hi> (like Great <hi>Oaks</hi> pull'd up by an <hi>Hair</hi>) were removed; and an <hi>End</hi> was put to our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38400:6"/>
               <hi>Miſeries,</hi> and almoſt to our <hi>Fears,</hi> by a <hi>dry Victory;</hi> and our <hi>Redemption</hi> was not <hi>purchaſed</hi> by <hi>Fields</hi> of <hi>Blood</hi> either of our <hi>Friends,</hi> or <hi>Enemies.</hi> All things were unaccountably reduced into that firm State out of which they were diſtorted, and we are once again the <hi>Honour</hi> and the <hi>Envy</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> We are ſecured of our Ancient Laws, and Immunities by which we may live the Lives of <hi>reaſonable</hi> Creatures, and not of <hi>Machines</hi> or <hi>meer Bodies;</hi> (as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Slaves are rendred, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18.13.) and our <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>regnant,</hi> by which we may live the Lives of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Saints.</hi> We may truly ſay, the <hi>Bible</hi> triumphs in this Deliverance; and the <hi>Northern Hereſy,</hi> as they <hi>reproachfully</hi> call'd it, hath got a glorious Victory over <hi>human Inventions,</hi> and <hi>their</hi> Catholick Religion. The <hi>Maintenance</hi> and <hi>Preſervation</hi> of which, we need not in the leaſt be ſolicitous about, ſince the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> of a GOD of Infinite <hi>Truth, cannot</hi> but be <hi>faithful</hi> when he hath <hi>promiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I ventur'd to open the Book; and with all poſſible Brevity have given you a tranſient View of the <hi>very worthy deeds</hi> done to <hi>this</hi> Nation when His <hi>Majeſty</hi> was our <hi>Deliverer;</hi> Services they were ſo <hi>brave,</hi> but withal ſo very <hi>deſperate,</hi> that nothing but the <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturing</hi> into the <hi>Mouth</hi> of a <hi>Cannon</hi> to ſave a Friend, (and <hi>greater danger has no Man;</hi>) can give any juſt <hi>Idea</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>Speak <hi>Ireland</hi> (for He was <hi>thy Saviour</hi> alſo), when a Sound of <hi>Battel,</hi> and of <hi>great deſtruction</hi> was in thy Land; Speak, how <hi>He</hi> gave thy Enemies as the Duſt to his Sword; and as driven Stubble to his Bow; <hi>Say,</hi> what hardneſs he endured as a good Soldier; what dangers he expoſed himſelf to in the <hi>High Places</hi> of the Field; how he gave no Sleep to his Eyes, nor Slumber to his Eye-lids, till he cauſed their Swords to fall out of their Hands, turning to Flight the Armies of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38400:6"/>
               <hi>Aliens,</hi> and made Thee at laſt to dwell in <hi>Safety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtill his <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Travel</hi> is not over; for now he muſt croſs the Tempeſtuous <hi>Ocean,</hi> to plead the Cauſe, and contend for the <hi>Common</hi> Safety of <hi>this Side</hi> of the <hi>World;</hi> with <hi>an Adverſary whoſe Hand was againſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man, and every Man's hand againſt him;</hi> and what the <hi>Succeſs</hi> and <hi>Concluſion</hi> of the <hi>whole</hi> Matter hath been, ask <hi>this</hi> very Day, and it will tell thee. For,</p>
            <p n="2">(2) By <hi>Him,</hi> this <hi>Man of Reſt, We</hi> (and <hi>they</hi> both) enjoy <hi>great Quietneſs</hi> (or
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Peace</hi>); Reſt on <hi>every</hi> ſide, So that there is neither <hi>Adverſary,</hi> nor <hi>Evil Occurrent.</hi> The 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Thing to be Spoken to.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Peace</hi> is the <hi>Intention</hi> and <hi>End</hi> as well as the <hi>Ground</hi> of <hi>Lawful War.</hi> Deſired and Embraced by the Moſt Valiant, devoted to <hi>Martial Atchievements</hi> as the <hi>height</hi> of his <hi>Honour,</hi> and the <hi>utmoſt</hi> of his <hi>Ambition,</hi> as not to be purchaſed by the <hi>Excellencies</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> or all the Riches in the World. In reſpect to which the Poet ſings of the Warlike <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Thracians;</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Ocium Bello furioſa Thrace, (ſuband. rogat.</l>
                  <l>Ocium Medi Pharetra decori:</l>
                  <l>Groſphe, non Gemmis ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Purpura ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale, nec Auro.
<note place="margin">Hor. lib. 2. Od. 16.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Soldiers of <hi>Fortune,</hi> that make a <hi>Trade</hi> of War, (I hope <hi>that Trade</hi> that hath <hi>broke</hi> all <hi>others,</hi> will <hi>break it ſelf</hi> at laſt) are content, like the <hi>Eſtridg,</hi> to eat Iron, and live upon the Sword: Yet They that take up the Sword <hi>only</hi> upon an <hi>Honourable Neceſſity,</hi> will be glad to think an <hi>honeſt Convenience</hi> a <hi>Cogent Neceſſity</hi> to lay it down again: and afterwards look upon it to be as great an Honour and Happineſs to live by their <hi>Head piece</hi> as their Sword.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:38400:7"/>
            <p> The Diſciples of our Lord and Saviour, weread, were once afraid of their own Maſter as if they had ſeen a <hi>Spirit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 14.27.</note> Thus many when they ſee <hi>Peace coming,</hi> are <hi>afraid,</hi> and think it's an <hi>Apparition:</hi> but what <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to <hi>Them,</hi> His <hi>Majeſty</hi> has been pleaſed to ſay to <hi>us, Be not afraid, it is I that bring you the glad Tidings of Peace.</hi> Thus after a weary <hi>Week</hi> comes a <hi>Sabbath</hi> of Reſt. God has not only deliver'd us, not only <hi>raiſed</hi> us from the <hi>Grave,</hi> and comforted us with the Hopes that we ſhall not <hi>fall</hi> back into the <hi>ſame</hi> Grave again; (which comfort at the height of Affliction is like <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> at the <hi>Block;</hi>) but after a <hi>Sore</hi> and <hi>Tedious</hi> War hath given us the <hi>invaluable</hi> Bleſſing of <hi>Peace.</hi> We have, like <hi>Jonathan,</hi> received our <hi>Honey</hi> at the End of a <hi>Rod;</hi> and out of the Eater, hath come forth Sweetneſs.</p>
            <p>Who <hi>thought</hi> of this Twelve Months ago? There was ſuch <hi>ſmall</hi> or <hi>no</hi> appearance of ſuch a Thing, that we might ſay, If the Lord would make Windows in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or ſay, Drop down ye Heavens from above, and let the Skies pour down <hi>Peace,</hi> might <hi>this</hi> thing be? Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD doth often ſow his Bleſſings whilſt Men <hi>Sleep.</hi> Whilſt our <hi>Faith</hi> ſleeps as to the <hi>Belief,</hi> (and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he has been more gracious to <hi>us</hi> than <hi>Chriſt</hi> was to his <hi>own Country,</hi> Matt. 13.58.) and Our <hi>Hopes</hi> ſleep as to the <hi>Expectation</hi> of ſo great a Mercy, he comes <hi>privily,</hi> as it were, and lays it down by us upon our <hi>Pillows.</hi> Jer. 29.11. <hi>For I know the Thoughts that I think towards you, ſaith the Lord; thoughts of</hi> Peace, <hi>and not of evil, to give you an expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed End.</hi> And thus after all our Toſſings, has he brought us to <hi>that fair Haven</hi> of Quiet <hi>where we would be.</hi> Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the <hi>Trumpets ſound</hi> nothing but the welcome <hi>joys</hi> of our Common <hi>Safety;</hi> and the <hi>armed</hi> Troops in our Streets, <hi>march</hi> only as our <hi>Defence</hi> and <hi>Guard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was once, you know, ſaid of <hi>Claudian,</hi> That he wanted <hi>Matter</hi> ſuitable to the Excellency of his <hi>Wit;</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38400:7"/>but where is <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Eloquence</hi> worthy of <hi>this</hi> Subject? <hi>Such</hi> a <hi>Comprehenſive</hi> Bleſſing is <hi>Peace, ſuch</hi> a <hi>Circle</hi> of Bleſſings, that who can ſhew forth all its Praiſe? So that (my Brethren) you muſt e'en pardon me, if I am forced (like the <hi>Geographers</hi>) to ſet down a <hi>Line</hi> for a <hi>River,</hi> and a <hi>Spot</hi> for a <hi>whole Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As GOD hath delivered us from as dreadful a <hi>Judgment</hi> as we could <hi>fear,</hi> ſo <hi>Peace</hi> is as great a <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> as we can <hi>deſire.</hi> It is one of GOD's <hi>good</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> Gifts; when the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> could ſay <hi>no more,</hi> he ends all with, <hi>The Lord will bleſs his People with Peace, Pſalm</hi> 29.11. As <hi>Bread</hi> in the Lord's Prayer, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends <hi>all</hi> Neceſſaries that conduce to the preſervation of our <hi>Natural</hi> Lives; ſo <hi>Peace</hi> includes whatſoever is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to make Church and State happy, It is every way excellent. If we ſpeak of <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> lo! <hi>this</hi> is <hi>Good;</hi> if of <hi>Delight,</hi> lo! <hi>this</hi> is <hi>Pleaſant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Utile Dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci.</note> Among all the prodigious <hi>Paradoxes</hi> held in <hi>England,</hi> I think this is none, <hi>That Peace is not Good.</hi> It is ſo incomparably Good, that we cannot receive any due and adequate Thoughts of it, from any thing elſe but our own <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</hi> Pſalm 133.1. <hi>Behold how good and pleaſant a Thing it is!</hi> An <hi>Exceſſive</hi> kind of Praiſe; and the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Stile of Praiſe is to profeſs our <hi>Inability</hi> of Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; even as the Pſalmiſt uſeth to ſpeak of GOD, <hi>O how excell nt is thy Name!</hi> and, <hi>How great is thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs!</hi> He could not comprehend the <hi>One,</hi> nor expreſs the <hi>Other.</hi> Thus, ſince we cannot ſufficiently ſet out the Praiſes of <hi>Peace,</hi> we will only ask, How good it is? And Praiſe it, by ſaying <hi>Nothing</hi> of it. We can only ask the Queſtion, How Good? and, How Pleaſant? But cannot anſwer it: However, He would try at it, and tells us, <hi>It's like the precious Ointment,</hi> &amp;c. What has a Fragrant Smell we all admire, and draw near to. <hi>Becauſe of the ſavour of thy good Ointments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1.</note> 
               <hi>we will run
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38400:8"/>after thee. Peace</hi> has an <hi>Attractive</hi> Power; for though Men naturally Love their <hi>own</hi> Country beſt, yet every Man likes beſt to live where there is <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Quiet. Iſaac</hi> left <hi>Gerar</hi> when they <hi>Strove</hi> with him,
<note place="margin">Gen 26.17, &amp;c.</note> and went to <hi>Sitnah</hi> for <hi>Peace;</hi> and when they <hi>Strove</hi> with him there, he went to <hi>Rehoboth,</hi> and <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> for <hi>Peace.</hi> And <hi>England</hi> can tell what a <hi>Conflux</hi> of <hi>French,</hi> &amp;c. have come over, and ſtill continue amongſt us for the ſhadow of our <hi>Peace;</hi> inſomuch that we have been like <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s <hi>Tree,</hi> a <hi>Shade,</hi> and a <hi>Refuge to all the Fowls of the Air,</hi> and <hi>the Beaſts of the Field;</hi> and not only the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>our Church</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> but the great <hi>Houſe</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) hath been <hi>filled</hi> with the ſweet <hi>Savour</hi> of <hi>this</hi> our good <hi>Ointment.</hi> And as it is indeed like <hi>Ointment,</hi> ſo it is like the <hi>Dew;</hi> thus compared to ſhew its <hi>fertility,</hi> according to the known Nature of it in <hi>fructifying</hi> the Earth; not to <hi>Rain,</hi> which ſometimes falling with Violence, doth more hurt than good; but to a diſtilling <hi>Dew,</hi> frequently called <hi>the Dew of Heaven.</hi> Thus Peace is of <hi>Celeſtial Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> the <hi>Ointment</hi> is <hi>pour'd</hi> on by the Hand of a <hi>Man;</hi> and our <hi>Peace</hi> is well promoted by <hi>Inferior</hi> Means; but the <hi>Dew</hi> comes from <hi>Heaven;</hi> and it is GOD that ſends the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> of <hi>Peace;</hi> and as the Influences of Heaven fatten the Earth, ſo does this a Church and Nation. Nay, It's <hi>as the dew of Hermon,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal reads it,</hi> As the Dew of Hermon that deſcended upon the mountains of Zion; <hi>And ſo the</hi> Greek <hi>Verſion Renders it as the Vulgar</hi> Latin. <hi>Now in regard theſe Two ſeem'd to be far diſtant, the</hi> One <hi>in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>the</hi> Other <hi>beyond</hi> Jordan; <hi>and ſo</hi> impoſſible <hi>that the</hi> Dew <hi>of</hi> One <hi>ſhould run down to the</hi> Other; <hi>divers</hi> late <hi>Tranſlations, with Ours, have added,</hi> And as the Dew; <hi>as if</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>it were to be repeated. But there are ſome Learned Interpreters that think it not neceſſary, in regard there was a</hi> Zion <hi>alſo near</hi> Jordan, <hi>adjoining to</hi> Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.48. Unto Mount Sion which is Hermon. <hi>And howſoever in the</hi> Hebrew <hi>there is ſome</hi> Literal <hi>difference between</hi> Sion <hi>and</hi> Zion, <hi>here and in the Pſalm; yet they take it not to be of any Conſequence, in regard there may be given divers Inſtances of ſuch Varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and greater in the Names of the ſame Perſons and Places.</hi>
               </note> which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38400:8"/>was one of the richeſt Soils in all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to denote the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of the Benefit that will redound hereby. It is <hi>ſo</hi> profitable, that if you were <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> of <hi>all</hi> things beſides, and <hi>this</hi> was wanting, <hi>they could profit you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> And therefore, <hi>How good is it?</hi> Is as if <hi>nothing</hi> was <hi>good without it,</hi> according to the <hi>Greek</hi> Verſion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. What is good,</hi> but for Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to dwell in Peace? There is no <hi>real</hi> Bleſſing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; take this away, and you deſtroy a Kingdom. As the <hi>Artificer</hi> Carved <hi>his own Name</hi> into the Buckler of <hi>Minerva</hi> ſo exactly, that whoſoever ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to pick <hi>it</hi> out, muſt of neceſſity <hi>ſpoil</hi> the <hi>Buckler;</hi> ſo it is with <hi>Peace;</hi> which is ſo <hi>woven</hi> with the <hi>Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of a Kingdom, that whoſoever <hi>deſtroys Peace, deſtroys</hi> a <hi>Kingdom.</hi> The <hi>Hebrews</hi> comprehended <hi>all manner</hi> of <hi>Proſperity</hi> under its Name; an Obſervation as common as their Vulgar Salutation, <hi>Peace be unto you;</hi> which is equivolent with that of <hi>Ours, I wiſh you all Happinſs;</hi> and hereupon they uſed the word at <hi>every turn,</hi> and upon every occaſion; inſomuch that it is ſometimes put, by a <hi>Catechreſis,</hi> to ſignify the <hi>Proſperous</hi> Succeſs even of <hi>War</hi> it ſelf; 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.7. <hi>David</hi> Commanded of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah, how Joab did,</hi> and <hi>how the people did,</hi> and <hi>concerning the Peace of the War,</hi> that is (as our Tranſlators Render it) <hi>how the War proſpered?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now ſince I have mentioned that <hi>unlucky</hi> Word <hi>War,</hi> let your fancy lead you for a while into ſome Kingdom where the Weapons of War <hi>(the Weapons of the Lord's indignation)</hi> are brought forth. You need no other <hi>Foil</hi> to ſet off the <hi>Luſtre</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> of this <hi>Jewel</hi> of <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imagine then that you ſee <hi>War</hi> Riding upon a <hi>Red</hi> Horſe, and he <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbridled;</hi> with his Sword wearied and <hi>blunted</hi> by Deſtruction, and <hi>made fat with fatneſs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 34.16.</note> How <hi>diſmal</hi> is the <hi>ſight!</hi> How <hi>dreadful</hi> is the <hi>Place!</hi> it is no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38400:9"/>other than the Gate of <hi>Hell.
<note place="margin">Joel 2.1, 2. 2 Kings 8.12.</note> Joel</hi> calls the Day of War, a Day of <hi>Gloomineſs</hi> and thick pitchy <hi>Darkneſs. Eliſha wept to think of it.</hi> So that <hi>David</hi> was much in the right when the Prophet put him to his <hi>Trilemma,</hi> to chuſe the <hi>Plague</hi> rather than the <hi>other Two;</hi> and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to beſeech, <hi>Let me not fall into the Hand of Man, whoſe very Mercies are Cruelty.</hi> Which may be <hi>one</hi> Reaſon why <hi>Nebuchadnezzar Seal'd</hi> the Den of Lions wherein <hi>Daniel</hi> was, becauſe he thought it ſafer to truſt him with the <hi>Lions</hi> than with his <hi>implacable Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>War is a <hi>Colluvies</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Evil both of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Miſery;</hi> then behold a <hi>Troop</hi> comes; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; if they call'd it <hi>the Father of all,</hi> you may well add <hi>Miſchief</hi> to make up the <hi>Senſe.</hi> It's the very <hi>Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Deſolation; <hi>abominable</hi> for the Outrages com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in it; and making <hi>Deſolate</hi> in the ſad and woful Effects of it.</p>
            <p>He was an <hi>Ingenious</hi> Limner, who moſt <hi>Lively</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented a <hi>Dying</hi> Piece in this manner: A Goodly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron <hi>Mortally</hi> Wounded at the Storming of a City; as ſhe lay Bleeding and Expiring of her Wound, behold her helpleſs hungry <hi>Infant</hi> comes <hi>crawling</hi> towards her Breaſts, whilſt the Dying <hi>Mother</hi> looks <hi>Wiſtly</hi> and <hi>Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> upon it; <hi>Nè Sanguis metuens pro Lacte bibatur;</hi> fearing leſt the Hungry Babe ſhould ſuck down <hi>Blood</hi> inſtead of <hi>Milk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No reſpect <hi>then</hi> to Perſons: <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Family</hi> do but at <hi>that</hi> Time make the Condition the more deplorable; for the <hi>higher</hi> they ſtand, the more open and expos'd are they to the <hi>Storm</hi> and <hi>Envy</hi> of Others. Riches are then but <hi>gilded Thorns,</hi> and Honour but an <hi>higher Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</hi> No Reverence then to <hi>Grey</hi> Hairs, no Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for <hi>Children,</hi> or <hi>thoſe that ſuck the Breaſts;</hi> no Compaſſion for the moſt Lovely and Charming <hi>Flowers</hi> of Beautiful <hi>Youth</hi> it ſelf. The <hi>Bed</hi> doth not protect
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38400:9"/>the <hi>Sick</hi> Perſon; nor the <hi>Woman</hi> the <hi>Burthen</hi> that ſhe carries; nor the <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> the <hi>Magiſtrate;</hi> nor the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> which is made in the moſt <hi>literal</hi> Senſe a <hi>Den</hi> of <hi>Thieves;</hi> So that there can be no coming to <hi>Church,</hi> no <hi>publick</hi> Devotion, without the danger of the <hi>Galileans Fate, to have their Blood ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with their Sacrifices;</hi> and for fear of being <hi>Numbred</hi> with the <hi>Dead,</hi> that (Cruel Wretches as they are) cannot <hi>reſt</hi> from their Labours, or Sleep in quiet for them. What <hi>Burning</hi> of <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Villages!</hi> What Slaughter and Havock of <hi>Human</hi> Fleſh and Blood!
<note place="margin">Iſa. 34.3.</note> the Mountains being <hi>melted</hi> with it, and the Fields become a diſmal <hi>Golgatha,</hi> groaning under the <hi>Weight</hi> of the <hi>Slain,</hi> and the <hi>Half-ſlain</hi> that <hi>beg</hi> for the <hi>Mercy</hi> to be <hi>quite</hi> Knocked o'th' Head.</p>
            <p>What Cries and Ejulations! What wringing the Hands, and tearing the Hair, of poor <hi>Widows</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans!</hi> What <hi>Rapes</hi> mingled with <hi>Murthers,</hi> and <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> with <hi>Rapes;</hi> Soldiers Killing Soldiers in the <hi>very moments</hi> of their ungoverned Luſts, to perpetrate the <hi>ſame</hi> Villanies themſelves!</p>
            <p>Whole Families <hi>ſtript naked</hi> of all their Enjoyments, how do they ſit <hi>Solitary</hi> and <hi>Forlorn!</hi> aggravating their Miſery, by viewing over the Records of their <hi>former</hi> Proſperity, and <hi>pleaſant</hi> Things; of which, alas! they have been <hi>plundered</hi> over and over, by one Party or another; ſo that what <hi>the Palmer-worm has left,
<note place="margin">Joel 1.4.</note> the Locuſts, Canker worm, and the Caterpillar has eaten;</hi> and they whoſe <hi>Goods,</hi> &amp;c. eſcape the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Hazael,</hi> are yet devoured by <hi>Jehu</hi>'s; till <hi>they</hi> have <hi>ſucked</hi> the <hi>very marrow</hi> out of thoſe <hi>Bones</hi> which <hi>others</hi> had <hi>broken;</hi> and ſhould any thing <hi>chance</hi> to have been <hi>left,</hi> yet that very little is ſo <hi>imbitter'd</hi> by <hi>frights</hi> and <hi>alarms</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi> the <hi>Caldeans</hi> and the <hi>Sabeans,</hi> that it cannot poſſibly be enjoy'd with any Satisfaction, but the <hi>Morſel</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:38400:10"/>is <hi>Eat</hi> with a <hi>trembling</hi> hand, and the <hi>Cup</hi> is drunk out of with a <hi>perpetual ſhaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How are the <hi>Rivers</hi> and <hi>Ponds died</hi> again with <hi>Purple</hi> Gore! by tumbling in Carcaſſes, and Men <hi>headlong</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that endeavouring to <hi>crawl out,</hi> are <hi>knock'd down</hi> again, and ſo <hi>periſh</hi> in the <hi>Waters;</hi> whilſt <hi>Others</hi> are fain to <hi>ſly</hi> for their Lives; the <hi>Woods</hi> and <hi>Mountains</hi> wanting <hi>Caves</hi> and <hi>hiding-places</hi> for them; being never likely to <hi>meet</hi> their <hi>dear Relations</hi> again in <hi>this</hi> World; <hi>Some</hi> of them leading a <hi>tedious</hi> life in a <hi>far</hi> Country; <hi>Others</hi> periſhing by the way; and the <hi>Reſt,</hi> it's to be feared, taken <hi>Captive,</hi> to be <hi>Slaves,</hi> it may be, to <hi>Slaves;</hi> a Caſe ſo <hi>very pitiable,</hi> that it made the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>forbid to weep for the dead, but bid weep ſorely for them that are going away,</hi> Jer. 22.10.</p>
            <p>As thoſe Three Commandments, <hi>Thouſhalt not Kill, Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery, Thou ſhalt not Steal,</hi> are ranked <hi>together</hi> in the <hi>Law;</hi> ſo are they uſually <hi>violated</hi> in the Lawleſs Violence of <hi>War;</hi> and ſo you find them threatned <hi>together,</hi> Iſa. 13.16. <hi>Their children ſhall be daſhed in pieces before their eyes, their houſes ſpoiled, and their wives raviſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> is a ſhort,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aſ.</hi> in Querim. Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> but a ſmart and pithy Examination of the <hi>Soldiers Pater Noſter;</hi> by which, <hi>with ſome little Alteration of it,</hi> you may give a gueſs at the <hi>deplorable</hi> Condition of <hi>that</hi> Country which is <hi>wounded with the wound of an enemy,
<note place="margin">Jer. 30.14.</note> and the chaſtiſement of a cruel one.</hi> Quid quaeſo Orat Miles? &amp;c. <hi>What, I beſeech you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>or How does the Soldier Pray?</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Doſt thou ſay, <hi>Our Father?</hi> Impudent Mouth! How dareſt thou call GOD <hi>Father,</hi> that art ſlying at thy <hi>Brother's Throat,</hi> or the <hi>next</hi> thou meeteſt, to <hi>cut</hi> or <hi>tear</hi> it out?</p>
               <p>Doſt thou ſay, <hi>Hallowed be thy Name;</hi> when GOD's Name is by none more <hi>Blaſphemed</hi> and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38400:10"/>
                  <hi>Diſhonoured</hi> than by thy <hi>unhallowed</hi> Lips, and thy Fellow-Soldiers rending the very Heavens by their Oaths and Execrations?</p>
               <p>Doſt thou ſay, <hi>Thy Kingdom come;</hi> when none is a greater <hi>Enemy</hi> to the Kingdom of <hi>Grace,</hi> than thy wicked ſelf?</p>
               <p>Doſt thou ſay, <hi>Thy will be done on Farth as it is in Heaven;</hi> and yet when GOD tells thee it is <hi>his</hi> will thou ſhouldeſt <hi>follow Peace with all men,</hi> thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt to <hi>put the Blood of War upon thy Girdle that's about thy Loins; and ſleepeſt not except thou haſt done Miſchief, except thou cauſeſt ſome to fall,</hi> thou Enemy of all Righteouſneſs?</p>
               <p>Doſt thou ſay, <hi>Give us this day our daily Bread;</hi> and yet takeſt away by <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Rapine</hi> all the Neceſſaries of Life thy Neighbour hath labour'd for in the Sweat of his Brows, and leaveſt nothing that pertains to him by the <hi>Morning</hi> Light?</p>
               <p>Thou beſeecheſt the Lord <hi>to forgive thee thy Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes,</hi> but certainly thou dareſt go <hi>no farther,</hi> but muſt make a <hi>Full Stop</hi> where Chriſt made but a <hi>Comma;</hi> For how canſt thou add, <hi>As thou Forgiveſt them that Treſpaſs againſt thee,</hi> when nothing but thy Brother's <hi>Blood</hi> will ſatisfy thee, and his too who never did nor would have offended thee, hadſt thou not firſt out of Meaſure provoked him?</p>
               <p>Doſt thou Pray, <hi>Not to be led into Temptation,</hi> and yet accounteſt it <hi>Puſillanimity</hi> not to venture upon any Thing that thy <hi>Ravenous</hi> Appetite or Luſts Tempt thee unto?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Doſt thou Supplicate <hi>to be Delivered from all Evil,</hi> and yet are not aſhamed, nor doſt thou bluſh to commit <hi>Abominations, (Seven</hi> Abominations are in thy Heart) and to appoint whatever thou comeſt near to utter deſtruction, and makeſt it thy Trade to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38400:11"/>live all thy days in that <hi>Evil of Evils,</hi> Bloody War, that maketh a Land which is <hi>before</hi> an Army, <hi>as the Garden of Eden</hi> to be <hi>behind</hi> it, a <hi>deſolate Wilderneſs; more deſolate than the Wilderneſs towards Diblath?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Such,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nah. 2.3. Hoſ. 2.18.</note> in Truth, is the <hi>Nature</hi> and uncontrouled <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> of the Men that are in <hi>Scarlet; ſuch</hi> their <hi>Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Circumſtances</hi> that are <hi>oppreſſed</hi> with the <hi>Bow,</hi> the <hi>Sword,</hi> and the <hi>Battel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as by <hi>War</hi> in the <hi>Great,</hi> ſo by <hi>War</hi> in the <hi>Little</hi> World, <hi>the Body of Man,</hi> we may <hi>know and ſee what an Evil thing it is, and bitter</hi> to be deprived of this <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> of <hi>Peace;</hi> and conſequently what a <hi>Value</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> to put upon it.</p>
            <p>If that <hi>General League</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> that great <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Pacis,</hi> the juſt <hi>Temperament</hi> of the Body, be not <hi>preſerved</hi> and <hi>kept entire,</hi> How doleful are the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences! How are all <hi>Proceedings</hi> in all the <hi>Courts</hi> of Nature <hi>ſtopt;</hi> and all <hi>Actions, Natural, Vital,</hi> and <hi>Animal,</hi> very much <hi>hindred</hi> and <hi>retarded,</hi> if not <hi>let fall!</hi> How is all <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Commerce</hi> forbidden, though the <hi>ſeveral Parts</hi> of Nature are Nouriſhed <hi>from</hi> and <hi>by each other!</hi> How is Nature <hi>ſhut up,</hi> and all the Paſſages <hi>ſtopt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg 5.6.</note> and <hi>the high ways are unoccupied, and the travellers</hi> (the <hi>Spirits,</hi> the <hi>Blood,</hi> and the other <hi>neceſſary Humours preternaturally) walk through by-paths!</hi> and there is no <hi>coming in</hi> of uſual and neceſſary Supplies, nor <hi>going out</hi> for thoſe <hi>(Excrementitious)</hi> Humours, which are ſuch a <hi>Burthen</hi> and <hi>Weakning</hi> to Nature's <hi>Gariſon,</hi> that it cannot <hi>hold out.</hi> In a word; The <hi>Seditious within</hi> are at ſuch Conteſts one with another, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>complaining in its Streets.</hi> The <hi>Keepers</hi> of the Houſe (the <hi>Arms) Tremble;</hi> and the <hi>Strong Men</hi> (thoſe <hi>Supporters</hi> of the Houſe, the <hi>Legs) bow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;</hi> and <hi>the ſound of the grinding is low,</hi> and <hi>thoſe that look out at the Windows</hi> (the <hi>Eyes</hi>) are <hi>darkned;</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:38400:11"/>and the <hi>Doors</hi> (the <hi>Mouth, Ears,</hi> &amp;c) <hi>are ſhut in the Streets,</hi> and the <hi>Voice of a</hi> little chirping <hi>Bird</hi> awakens, and <hi>all the Daughters of Muſick are brought low (low</hi> as to his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Capacity to uſe</hi> them, for his Voice fails; and <hi>low</hi> as to any <hi>Eſteem</hi> he hath of them, for he regards them not;) <hi>fear alſo poſſeſſeth him, and the Graſhopper is a Burden to him, and his deſire fails.</hi> Thus lies he on his <hi>Bed</hi> of <hi>Languiſhing;</hi> which though never ſo <hi>ſoft,</hi> can afford him no <hi>Eaſe,</hi> unleſs GOD be pleaſed to <hi>make</hi> it; ſo that he would willingly exchange his Bed of <hi>Down</hi> for one of <hi>Duſt;</hi> and his <hi>Soul chuſeth ſtrangling and death rather than Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now (My Brethren) put what I have ſaid together, from conſiderations taken from <hi>both</hi> Worlds, <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> to be in a <hi>State</hi> of <hi>War;</hi> and it muſt needs be that you will preſently <hi>fall in Love,</hi> and <hi>pay your Court</hi> to this Beauty of <hi>Peace,</hi> which is the perfect <hi>Reverſe</hi> of all that has been ſpoken. And therefore ſince <hi>it</hi> is at laſt <hi>returnd</hi> to <hi>us</hi> from <hi>afar,</hi> let us <hi>lay hold</hi> of it; as the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs</hi> did <hi>apprehend</hi> the <hi>Promiſes.</hi> Heb. 11.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they <hi>Saluted</hi> them, they <hi>hugg'd</hi> them, they <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced</hi> them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peace</hi> like the <hi>Vernal Sun</hi> gives <hi>new Life</hi> and <hi>Vigor</hi> to the World, and makes its Inhabitants, like the <hi>Hills</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> to <hi>laugh</hi> and <hi>ſing.</hi> It <hi>whets</hi> mens Diligence and Induſtry in their ſeveral Callings; giving them hopes that their lawful Undertakings ſhall return <hi>Crowned</hi> with their deſired Effects. It is the <hi>Spring</hi> of all <hi>Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and gives a <hi>free Communication</hi> from One End of the World to the Other, that we ſhare in the good things intruſted by GOD and <hi>Nature</hi> with <hi>other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and Perſons. It is ſo Excellent, that the Orator
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dulce eſt Nomen Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis; res tam jucunda, &amp; ſalutaris, qud non modo ii quibus ſenſum Natura dedit, ſea ettam Tecta atque agri laetari videntur.</hi> Cic.</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:38400:12"/>tells us, not only ſuch as have <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> but the very <hi>Fields</hi> and <hi>Houſes</hi> rejoice in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peace,</hi> it's the <hi>Soul</hi> of the Univerſe, the <hi>Chain</hi> of the World, and the <hi>Cement</hi> of Nature. <hi>Peace,</hi> it's the <hi>Beauty</hi> of Providence, the <hi>Bond</hi> of Governments, and the <hi>Mother</hi> of Order. <hi>Peace,</hi> the <hi>Life</hi> of the Law, the <hi>Guardian</hi> of Learning, and the <hi>Encouragement</hi> of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. <hi>Peace,</hi> the <hi>Health</hi> of the People, the Sojourner's <hi>Safety,</hi> and the Enemies <hi>Terror.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further yet, for the <hi>better</hi> half has not been told you. <hi>Peace,</hi> it's the great deſign of the Ever-bleſſed TRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NITY. The <hi>Promiſe</hi> of the <hi>Father;</hi> who has done <hi>this</hi> Vertue the <hi>Honour</hi> to ſtile himſelf from it, The GOD of <hi>Peace,</hi> Rom. 15.33. 2 Theſſ. 3.16. The <hi>Purchaſe</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> who is the <hi>Prince of Peace,</hi> Iſa. 6.9. and the <hi>Product</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> who is ſet forth to us by <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace,</hi> Epheſ. 4.3. At the <hi>Birth</hi> of Our Saviour the Angels chanted it forth,—<hi>On Earth Peace.</hi> The <hi>Excellency</hi> of his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings is couched in this, that <hi>They were the Chaſtiſements of his Peace,</hi> Iſa. 53.5. and He himſelf Publiſhed it at his <hi>Reſurrection—Peace be with you.</hi> And, <hi>by the way,</hi> it may not here be improper to make one <hi>Remark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our dear Lord, though content to be <hi>Crucify'd</hi> on <hi>Mount Calvary;</hi> yet, whilſt he was living, he was moſt delighted to be in the <hi>Mount</hi> of <hi>Olives.</hi> He lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his Life in a place of <hi>Skulls,</hi> an Emblem of <hi>War;</hi> (where truly he is <hi>ſtill Crucified;</hi>) but he leads his Life moſt commonly in a place of <hi>Olives,</hi> an <hi>Emblem</hi> of <hi>Peace;</hi> there he prays, there he preaches, there he walks, contemplates, and watches; doth every thing but die; that was reſerved for Mount <hi>Calvary:</hi> Yea, thence he aſcends into Heaven; and as <hi>Peace</hi> was one of the <hi>laſt</hi> Legacies his Lips bequeathed us when he dy'd, ſo Mount <hi>Olives</hi> (the dwelling-place of <hi>Peace</hi>)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38400:12"/>was the <hi>laſt</hi> piece of Earth his bleſſed Foot touched when he aſcended. But to return, and I ſhall only ſpeak this Once. <hi>Peace,</hi> it's the <hi>Reconciliation</hi> of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the <hi>Conſolation</hi> of the Saints, and the <hi>Crown</hi> of the Bleſſed. <hi>Peace,</hi> at which the <hi>Scriptures</hi> aim, <hi>Faith</hi> intends, <hi>Hope</hi> aſpires to, and it is compleat <hi>Beatitude</hi> to attain it. And therefore <hi>happy</hi> muſt <hi>that People</hi> needs be, that are in <hi>ſuch</hi> a Caſe, whom GOD hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented with <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> Bleſſing It is <hi>our own</hi> Caſe, <hi>bleſſed be the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 68.19. Pſ. 92.17.</note> who daily loads us with his Beneſits: The Beauty of the Lord our GOD is upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s;</hi> and we have lived to ſee the <hi>Dove</hi> and the <hi>Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branch</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Peace lighting</hi> upon the <hi>Head</hi> of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Perhaps, we may think we have <hi>deſerved</hi> as much at GODs hand. It may be it has been our <hi>Strictneſs</hi> and <hi>Exactneſs</hi> of Converſation before him; our <hi>Care</hi> of his <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Vindication</hi> of his <hi>Truth;</hi> our <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of his <hi>Sabbaths, &amp;c.</hi> perhaps it has been our <hi>Charity,</hi> our <hi>Hamility</hi> and <hi>Sobriety,</hi> which <hi>ſo far have prevail'd</hi> upon him; Surely it is becauſe he hath not ſpy'd in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> thoſe <hi>Luſts</hi> and horrible <hi>Abominations</hi> which he hath beheld in ſome <hi>other Times</hi> and <hi>Places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O <hi>Prophane</hi> I magination! Let not ſuch vain Thoughts lodge within us. Should GOD have gone by <hi>this</hi> Rule, we had <hi>long, long</hi> ſince been in <hi>Ruins.</hi> Let us <hi>rather</hi> ſay, it's the <hi>free</hi> Grace of that GOD who <hi>is good,</hi> and <hi>doth good.</hi> Who hath Shewed favour to <hi>this</hi> Kingdom, becauſe he would ſhew Favour, (as though he would be called the GOD of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi>) inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>We</hi> of all others <hi>have comprehended</hi> (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>been comprehended by) the Breadth, and Length, and Depth, and Height</hi> of GOD's <hi>Love.</hi> The Philoſophers tell us but of <hi>Three</hi> Dimenſions, the Apoſtle has ſound out <hi>Four</hi> in GOD's Mercy, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.18. Let us
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38400:13"/>
               <hi>rather</hi> think that we enjoy the Benefit of the Graces of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and other <hi>Holy</hi> Perſons, who, by their <hi>Prayers,</hi> and <hi>Votes</hi> whilſt they were here below, reſerved a ſpecial Bleſſing for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> in theſe Succeeding Times. And this will engage our Hearts to the practice of thoſe Duties which the <hi>Kindneſs that has been done unto us,</hi> ſo juſtly deſerves at our hands. The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> and the laſt Thing to be ſpoken to. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">Deut Nob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta.</note> Let us aſcribe <hi>this</hi> Mercy to GOD with all Thankfulneſs. We muſt not look upon <hi>this Peace</hi> as a Matter of <hi>Chance</hi> and <hi>Fortune;</hi> as the <hi>ſole</hi> product of <hi>humane Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Courage.</hi> It is true, Men are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> GOD's <hi>hands,</hi> as Herbaliſts call Plants: And <hi>theſe</hi> Hands of GOD we may <hi>kiſs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 14 11.</note> but let us be careful not to take the <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>Garlands</hi> which we ſhould lay at GOD's <hi>Feet,</hi> to ſet upon <hi>Man's Head.</hi> It is no <hi>diminution</hi> in the leaſt to <hi>His Majeſty</hi> that we aſcribe it to GOD. For what can ſo much dignify any Mortal Man, as to be an Inſtrument in GOD's hand, one whom he chuſes to bring about glorious Things by, and to convey Bleſſings to a Kingdom?</p>
            <p>To bring <hi>Peace</hi> out of <hi>War,</hi> is a Work <hi>worthy</hi> of GOD. Pſal. 46.9. He <hi>maketh Wars to ceaſe; he breaketh the Bow, and knappeth the Spear in ſunder, and burneth the Chariots in the Fire.</hi> And therefore that <hi>great</hi> Promiſe of <hi>Peace</hi> runs thus, <hi>They ſhall beat their Swords into Ploughſhares, and their Spears into Pruning-Hooks.</hi> Soldiers ſhall turn <hi>Vine dreſſers,</hi> and <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> the <hi>Bees</hi> ſhall <hi>hive</hi> in their <hi>Helmets. Nation ſhall not lift up Sword againſt Nation; That</hi> ſhall <hi>once for all</hi> be put up into its place,
<note place="margin">Non ſolum cum Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſed cum Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur Bellum.</note> and never be drawn again; <hi>Neither ſhall they learn War any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed days! when the <hi>Art Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lic</hi> or <hi>Military</hi> ſhall be out of date, and (being <hi>it ſelf</hi> the greateſt <hi>Interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of <hi>Learning</hi>) ſhall be <hi>learned</hi> no more. Thus again,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38400:13"/>
               <hi>Iſa</hi> 45.7. <hi>I form the Light (Civil</hi> as well as <hi>Natural); —I make Peace (Temporal</hi> as well as <hi>Spiritual); I the Lord do all theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We praiſe <hi>Thee</hi> therefore, O GOD, we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Thee</hi> who art the <hi>Lover,</hi> to be the Lord and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of <hi>our Peace</hi> and <hi>Concord. This</hi> is the <hi>day</hi> that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath made, we will <hi>rejoice,</hi> and be glad in it, <hi>even</hi> in the <hi>preſence</hi> of all <hi>thoſe</hi> that have an <hi>Evil</hi> Will at <hi>our Sion:</hi> That would have <hi>Peace,</hi> but <hi>not yet;</hi> that would have <hi>Peace,</hi> but <hi>they</hi> would <hi>proclaim it</hi> themſelves; and then I queſtion not but <hi>it</hi> would be <hi>juſt ſuch an One</hi> as our Country-man <hi>Galgacus</hi> in <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> ſpeaks of, in Relation to the <hi>Romans,</hi> whom he calls there, <hi>Raptores Orbis,</hi> the <hi>Robbers</hi> of the World, who when they have <hi>laid all Waſte</hi> as a <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> call <hi>Peace. Theſe</hi> are People that do <hi>err</hi> in their Hearts; the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Peace they</hi> have not known; but with <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Vengeance,</hi> and a <hi>raw, ſore</hi> Mind, ſtand <hi>muttering</hi> and <hi>murmuring without,</hi> whilſt <hi>in</hi> our Father's Houſe there is <hi>Feaſting</hi> and <hi>Muſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 126. that when the Lord turned the Captivity of <hi>Zion, we were like unto them that dream;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cajetan. in loc.</note> but the words ſhould rather be tranſlated, <hi>We are like unto thoſe that are reſtored to health;</hi> and it beſt ſuits with the <hi>following</hi> words, <hi>Then were our Mouths fill'd with Laughter,</hi> and <hi>our Tongues with Praiſe;</hi> which can never be ſaid of a Man when he <hi>dreams;</hi> but to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that is <hi>reſtor'd to Health</hi> after a tedious fit of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it is very applicable. Since therefore the Lord has turned <hi>Our</hi> Captivity as the Waters of the <hi>South,</hi> and we can truly ſay, <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> and <hi>our Health</hi> is <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd,</hi> let us praiſe the Lord. If he expects <hi>publick</hi> Thanks for <hi>private</hi> Mercies, much more then for <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. Pſ.</hi> 103.1. When therefore we hear <hi>ſuch</hi> a joyful Sound; ſo that as <hi>Balaam</hi> ſaid, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.21.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38400:14"/>GOD <hi>is with them,</hi> and <hi>the Shout of a King is amongſt them,</hi> as either <hi>conquering</hi> his Enemies, or giving them <hi>Rest</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> in his Name ſhould we rejoice and boaſt all the day long.</p>
            <p>Almighty GOD expects that his ſeveral diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould be entertained with ſuitable Deportments, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.14. <hi>In the day of Proſperity be joyful.</hi> Deut. 16.15. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſurely rejoice.</hi> As it is ſaid of the <hi>Jews</hi> upon the <hi>reſtoring</hi> and <hi>ſettling Jeruſalem</hi> in <hi>Peace,</hi> that they rejoiced, becauſe GOD <hi>made them to rejoice, Neh.</hi> 12.43. We ſhould <hi>delight</hi> our Selves in the <hi>Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> of <hi>Peace. Pſa.</hi> 37.11. <hi>Praiſe the Lord, O Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, praiſe thy GOD, O Sion; For He hath ſtrengthened the Bars of thy Gates, He hath bleſſed thy Children within thee; He maketh Peace in they Borders,</hi> Pſal. 147.12.</p>
            <p>To be Chagrin, Sullen, and out of Humour at ſuch a Time as this, is as ſuitable as to put on <hi>Mourning</hi> at a <hi>Wedding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quod exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit idem api.</note> or to <hi>Faſt</hi> on a <hi>Sunday.</hi> We are <hi>all</hi> of Us now (ſince <hi>every</hi> Man is <hi>concerned</hi> in the Benefit) to awaken <hi>all manner</hi> of <hi>decent</hi> Expedients whereby to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> our Thankfulneſs to GOD. Let the Horizon Eccho our joyful Acclamations; Let the <hi>Roofs</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> return the loud Voice of our <hi>common</hi> Praiſes. Let the <hi>whole</hi> Kingdom build <hi>Altars</hi> to the Lord, and call them, <hi>Jehova-Shalom,</hi> ſaying, <hi>the Lord hath bleſt his people with Peace.</hi> Let the <hi>Streets</hi> be <hi>fill'd</hi> with <hi>Melody,</hi> and our <hi>Houſes</hi> with <hi>Cheerfulneſs.</hi> Bring hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Tabret,</hi> the <hi>merry Harp,</hi> and <hi>the Lute.</hi> But after all, I would not be <hi>miſtaken</hi> in the Point. It is not a <hi>prophane</hi> Mirth that I am pleading for; that is an <hi>horrid</hi> Sin, and to be deteſted. The Publick <hi>Joy</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> is not to be expreſſed to the Publick <hi>diſgrace</hi> both of their <hi>Joy</hi> and their <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> We are not to allow our ſelves in any <hi>intemperate, unwarrantable</hi> Tranſports; in <hi>ſenſual</hi> Revellings, and <hi>Baccanal</hi> Rites;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38400:14"/>indulging to Extravagancy, and <hi>offending</hi> GOD whilſt we <hi>praiſe</hi> him. It would have been high <hi>Indiſcretion</hi> in <hi>Noah</hi> and his <hi>Family</hi> when in the Ark, and perceiving the <hi>Dove</hi> approaching with an <hi>Olive Branch,</hi> to have made ſuch a <hi>Noiſe</hi> and <hi>Lumber</hi> as ſhou'd have <hi>frighted</hi> her away. It behoves Us to walk <hi>circumſpectly,</hi> not as <hi>Fools,</hi> but as <hi>Wiſe;</hi> not only as Men overjoy'd at <hi>preſent,</hi> but as <hi>circumſpect</hi> Perſons, Men <hi>careful</hi> to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</hi> what we rejoice in. Otherwiſe it may befall <hi>us</hi> as it doth ſome <hi>Young</hi> Heirs; who rejoice <hi>too</hi> much when they <hi>firſt</hi> come to a rich Inheritance; and ſo in a <hi>few</hi> Years by their profuſeneſs and <hi>prodigality,</hi> their <hi>Revenues</hi> and their <hi>Joy</hi> are <hi>both</hi> brought to an <hi>End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since we are called to <hi>rejoice,</hi> let it be with <hi>Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</hi> May we <hi>rejoice</hi> in GOD's goodneſs, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.25. and yet <hi>fear</hi> him, and his goodneſs, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.5. with ſuch a <hi>Syſtole</hi> and <hi>Diaſlole</hi> ought we to <hi>breathe</hi> and <hi>live:</hi> To <hi>rejoice</hi> with <hi>trembling,</hi> not out of diſtruſt of GOD, but <hi>our ſelves;</hi> not for fear GOD will not <hi>continue,</hi> but that <hi>we</hi> ſhall not <hi>deſerve</hi> our Happineſs. GOD forbid that <hi>the Tree of Fortune</hi> (as it is called) ſhould be ſo fairly <hi>Blown,</hi> that we might only ſee how great Hopes <hi>Sin</hi> is able to <hi>blaſt.</hi> We ought to have an holy <hi>fear,</hi> and <hi>trembling,</hi> of forſeiting our Mercies by our Sins. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.20. <hi>If you forſake the Lord, then will he turn, and do you hurt after he hath done you good.</hi> If we abuſe our <hi>Peace</hi> into Licentiouſneſs, and commit <hi>folly</hi> with our Mercies, this <hi>Dove</hi> will ſly away to make room for a devouring <hi>Faulcon</hi> that will <hi>make</hi> a <hi>Stoop</hi> like <hi>Lightning</hi> with nothing but <hi>Deſtruction</hi> and <hi>Ruin</hi> engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon her <hi>Varvells.</hi> And then we may e'en thank <hi>our ſelves</hi> for being the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of our <hi>own</hi> Miſery: For no man is hurt but by Himſelf, (ſaith the <hi>Moraliſt.</hi>) Great States, as Buildings, are cruſhed by their own Weight, (ſay <hi>Politicians.</hi>) Perſons and Kingdoms
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38400:15"/>are deſtroy'd through their own Wickedneſs (ſays the <hi>Divine.) Thy Deſtruction is of thy ſelf, O Iſrael,</hi> Hoſ. 13.21. <hi>Propriis transfigimur alis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I'll tell you a <hi>Short,</hi> and a <hi>ready</hi> way how we may be <hi>ſafe</hi> and <hi>happy,</hi> and continue a <hi>long</hi> Bleſſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Selves,</hi> and <hi>Poſterity.</hi> The way is, Am I out? — no ſure; the way is— Let the Time paſt of our Lives ſuffice to have lived directly contrary to our <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> and <hi>Duty.</hi> Let the Vices that reigned in the <hi>late</hi> Days of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy Memory,</hi> and, I'm afraid, ſtill continue to do ſo, not be ſo much as once named amongſt us as becometh Saints; and the thing is done: And <hi>Peace</hi> ſhall be upon <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Let us give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that be <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s, who has made <hi>even</hi> our <hi>Enemies</hi> to be at <hi>Peace</hi> with Us. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (all <hi>Superlatives.) We accept it always,</hi> and <hi>in all Places, with all Thankfulneſs.</hi> It is what the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects; returns of <hi>Gratitude</hi> not only to <hi>himſelf,</hi> but to the glorious <hi>Inſtruments</hi> likewiſe which he is pleaſed to make uſe of. It is <hi>reproachfully</hi> ſaid of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not only that they <hi>remembred not the Lord their GOD, who had deliverd them out of the hands of all their Enemies on every ſide;</hi> but that <hi>they ſhewed no kindneſs to the Houſe of Jerubb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al, namely Gideon</hi> (who had been his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in it) <hi>according to all the goodneſs which he had ſhewed unto Iſrael,</hi> Judges 8.34.</p>
            <p>We might <hi>wiſh</hi> (My Brethren) that <hi>Iſrael</hi> had been the <hi>only</hi> People in the World that had been guilty of <hi>ſuch ill</hi> treatment of their <hi>beſt</hi> Friends, and Benefactors. But <hi>that wiſh</hi> comes too late? We of <hi>this</hi> Nation <hi>abhor that Age</hi> that ſhall pretend to <hi>outdo ours</hi> in any Crime what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, not that of <hi>Ingratitude</hi> excepted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Very worthy deeds are done unto this Nation;</hi> We owe the correction of our <hi>Evil</hi> Fate, our <hi>Quiet</hi> and <hi>Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:38400:15"/>Lives to the <hi>King</hi>'s Providence; at the <hi>peril</hi> of <hi>his</hi> Life and Blood; which juſtly deſerves the <hi>tribute</hi> of our moſt Thankful Acknowledgments: But inſtead of <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing</hi> him for his <hi>Work's ſake;</hi> there are riſen up a <hi>Race</hi> of <hi>ſinful</hi> Men that will <hi>never forgive</hi> him, but are <hi>mad</hi> they have loſt the <hi>happineſs</hi> to be <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Slaves;</hi> and are reſolved to be <hi>peeviſh without Reaſon, rebellious without Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>troubleſome without End.</hi> The very <hi>Heathen</hi> World will riſe up in Judgment againſt <hi>ſuch</hi> a Generation, and condemn it: For they not only paid their <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Gracious</hi> Princes their Higheſt <hi>Honours</hi> during their <hi>Lives;</hi> but <hi>worſhipped</hi> them too after their <hi>Deaths.</hi> They could not imagine, that thoſe who either by the <hi>Invention</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Arts,</hi> or the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of an <hi>Excellent Government,</hi> or by many Noble <hi>Exploits</hi> and <hi>Deliverances,</hi> had in an high degree obliged their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, dy'd like <hi>other</hi> men; they reckon'd they became <hi>Divine,</hi> and were tranſlated among the GODS; and ſo changed their <hi>Allegiance</hi> into <hi>Adoration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs to you <hi>this</hi> ought <hi>not</hi> to be done; but then neither muſt the <hi>other</hi> be left undone: If it was but for <hi>this</hi> One <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Reaſon, that we might diſcover to the world the honour that we entertain for the <hi>Almighty</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who is the King of Kings. For in a proportion to that of 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.20. If we render not the Dues to theſe GODS whom we <hi>do ſee,</hi> (a <hi>ſtrain</hi> of Speech, that if <hi>Divine</hi> Authority did not warrant it,
<note place="margin">Pſal 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> would paſs for <hi>impudent,</hi> and <hi>blaſphemous</hi> Flattery) how ſhall we to <hi>Him</hi> whom we <hi>have not ſeen?</hi> How can we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the <hi>Supr am,</hi> that diſown the <hi>Subordinate</hi> Deities?</p>
            <p>Since therefore GOD hath <hi>ſetled</hi> us under <hi>ſuch</hi> an Auſpicious <hi>Monarch,</hi> who has ſo ſignally recommended himſelf to <hi>us,</hi> as he has done <hi>long ago</hi> to all the World beſide; at all times let us Congratulate our <hi>own Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and endeavour to make <hi>him</hi> happy too. Let us
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38400:16"/>
               <hi>Obey</hi> him <hi>humbly;</hi> if he be the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of GOD for our <hi>good,</hi> we ought to be <hi>Servants</hi> to him for his <hi>good.</hi> Let us <hi>honour</hi> him <hi>Conſcienciouſly,</hi> be <hi>Loyal</hi> upon <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> and for <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſake; not for hopes of <hi>Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> not by <hi>Chance,</hi> or <hi>good Fortune,</hi> not becauſe it may come into the <hi>Faſhion</hi> to be ſo, but becauſe GOD hath poſitively <hi>required</hi> it, and made it one ſpecial part of his unchangeable Law. Let us <hi>Love</hi> him Affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately; that there be no Striſe amongſt his Subjects, but to <hi>outvy</hi> each other in <hi>pious</hi> Loyalty; that the <hi>Hearts</hi> of his People may be his <hi>Throne.</hi> Laſtly, Let us <hi>Pray</hi> for him as we would do <hi>for our own Souls,</hi> That GOD would add many Years to his Life, yea, take from <hi>ours,</hi> who would moſt gladly <hi>ſpare</hi> them to add to <hi>his.</hi> That GOD would give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Faithful</hi> Council, a <hi>Royal</hi> People; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> omit nothing in our Prayers, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> give him his Hearts deſire and not withhold the requeſt of his Lips; that when be hath reigned <hi>many</hi> and <hi>many</hi> Years with all <hi>Proſperity</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> he may receive an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Crown,</hi> and leave <hi>Flouriſhing</hi> King, oms to his <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> and <hi>Peaceful</hi> Times to his <hi>Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) <hi>Pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> Pſal. 122.6. <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> ſignifies <hi>the Viſion of Peace;</hi> at <hi>firſt</hi> it was only cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Salem, Peace. Melchiſedech</hi> King of <hi>Salem,</hi> that is, King of <hi>Peace;</hi> but afterward when <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ireh</hi> was <hi>prefixed</hi> to <hi>Melchiſedech</hi>'s <hi>Salem,</hi> it became <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> a <hi>Viſion of Peace;</hi> then pray for the <hi>Peace</hi> of this <hi>Viſion of Peace.</hi> Bleſſed be GOD <hi>Our Jeruſalem</hi> is become a <hi>Viſion of Peace;</hi> then Pray for the <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>this Viſion of Peace; i. e.</hi> pray for the <hi>Continuance</hi> of it. The effectual Fervent Prayer of a Righteous Man availeth much; engages the Almighty, and calls in an Omnipotent Arm to <hi>Settle, Strengthen,</hi> and <hi>Secure</hi> our <hi>Peace.</hi> Such Pious Lips drop <hi>Balm</hi> upon the Countries
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38400:16"/>and Places where they live; and ſuch <hi>healing Tongues,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> calls them, are a <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> Prov. 15.4. but as for <hi>thoſe Tongues</hi> that cry concerning <hi>Jeruſalem, Down with it, down with it, even to the ground,</hi> may they cleave to the Roof of all their Mouths, that at the Hour of Death, they may not ſo much as ſay, <hi>Miſerere Domine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, As GOD hath done <hi>great</hi> things for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> ſo it is neceſſary we do <hi>ſomething</hi> again for <hi>Him;</hi> as he hath <hi>Given</hi> to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> ſo are we to <hi>Give</hi> to <hi>Him.</hi> Alas! How can that be? Since <hi>our goods reach not to him: He</hi> needs them not; true indeed, but <hi>His</hi> do: The <hi>Poor</hi> need, and by <hi>them</hi> our Goods reach even to <hi>Him</hi> too. We relieve <hi>Him</hi> in the <hi>Poor,</hi> and cloathe <hi>Him</hi> in the <hi>Naked;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25.45.</note> and no Time ſo <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> to do it in, none <hi>fitter</hi> than <hi>this;</hi> it's a proper <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for a <hi>Thanksgiving;</hi> let us make our <hi>Indigent</hi> Neighbours rejoice with us: That which would feed our <hi>Gluttony,</hi> and prove a <hi>provocation,</hi> being put into the Bellies of the Poor (and a <hi>Lazarus</hi> lies at <hi>every</hi> door) may plead our Pardon, and procure <hi>Mercy</hi> for <hi>Mercy.</hi> Let us break off our <hi>Sins</hi> by <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and our <hi>Iniquities</hi> by ſhewing <hi>Mercy to the Poor, it may be the lengthning of our Tranquility.</hi> Therefore having Refreſhed our ſelves, let us Cheer others, and deliver them from Diſtreſs and Want; <hi>Thoſe</hi> eſpecially who have ſuffered in the <hi>Battel;</hi> the <hi>Sick, Lame, Maimed;</hi> the deſolate <hi>Widows</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> as fell in the Service. Is there not all the reaſon in the World we ſhould Relieve <hi>them</hi> who with ſo much <hi>Alacrity</hi> have hazarded <hi>their Lives</hi> to preſerve <hi>ours?</hi> To whoſe <hi>Valour</hi> and <hi>Magnanimity</hi> we owe, in part, our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> nay, (and for ought we know) the <hi>Life</hi> of the KING.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:38400:17"/>
            <p> I Conclude all <hi>(Mutato Nomine)</hi> with that Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Joy which the People of <hi>Rome</hi> gave <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> at his Coronation;</p>
            <q>
               <p>GULIELMO <hi>Tertio, à</hi> DEO <hi>Coronato, Magno &amp; Pacifico Britannorum Imperatori Vita &amp; Victoria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To WILLIAM the Third, Crowned of GOD, the <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Peaceable</hi> Emperor of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> be <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Victory,</hi> and let the <hi>Three</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
